Hi everyone.
I'm Simon Willison and I've spent the
last four years building tools for data
analysis and exploration on top of sqlite.
I'm going to give you a tour of them.
Let's start with some data.
The Florida fish and wildlife conservation
commission released a data set of
Manatee carcass recovery locations in
Florida dating all the way back to 1974.
And they make that data
available as a CSV file. Here's
that CSV file.
I'm going to import that into a sqlite
database using a tool I wrote called
sqlite-utils. So I type
sqlite-utils insert. I'll
call the database manatees.db.
Table called locations. And
in goes that CSV file. Oh,
it wants me to add dash csv.
So I do that and now I have a file
called manatees.db. It's 2.8 megabytes.
Now I can do things like
I can ask for its schema.
It's got a table called locations
with a bunch of columns in.
I can also run some queries against it.
Let's do select county comma repdate
from locations, limit 10. There
we go. And that comes out as JSON.
If I add dash T I get that as a table.
I can even add fancy formats and say
things like dash fmt latex to get out a
latex representation of that ready for
me to paste into my academic paper.
Let's do something a bit more visual.
So I'm going to launch my data set
tool against that sqlite database.
So this is now running a local web
server. And if I click on here,
I get a web interface and I can
start browsing through that table.
Looks like a table of data,
but one of my favorite ways of exploring
a dataset that I'm used to is using
something called faceting.
So here's the dataset.
It's suggesting that the interesting
facets here might be the month, the sex,
the dcode, or the mortality.
Let's click on mortality.
So now this is showing me for these
13 and a half thousand sadly deceased
manatees what were the most common
causes of mortality for them?
So unsurprisingly, it was watercraft
collisions was a good fifth of them.
Natural cold stress. Human
related floodgate and canal
lock is the least common,
but it looks interesting so
I can click through that.
Now it's suggesting
that I facet by county.
I can see that Miami-Dade county is the
most dangerous county to be if you're a
manatee and you're worried about getting
trapped in a floodgate or canal lock.
So we're already beginning to learn
things about this data just through firing
it up in datasette and
starting to apply facets.
Everything you can see in datasette,
you can export back out again.
Here we've got 254 rows where
mortality was that canal lock.
And if we click on CSV, we can get back
just that subset of the data as CSV.
I can click on JSON to get it as JSON,
which is ready to be imported into
other programming environments.
But I can also click view and edit SQL
and see the actual SQL query that was run
to produce those results. And I can edit
it too. I'm gonna say, you know what,
I just want the tlength, state county,
these columns here for those rows.
And if I hit run SQL then I'll get back
that subset of the data. And again,
I can support that out as CSV, and
I can get that back as JSON. Now,
if you're thinking, hang on,
does this mean that I construct a SQL
query in my own client side JavaScript and
then run it against the server via this
URL here? The answer is yes, you can.
And it's not actually nearly
as bad idea as it sounds.
This might look like a SQL injection
vulnerability as a feature,
and indeed it is, but it's completely
safe for a couple of reasons. Firstly,
the database file itself is
opened in read-only mode.
So there is nothing that you can do
here that would modify that data as it
stored on disc. And secondly,
all of these SQL queries have a hard
time limit of a second applied to them.
If the query takes longer than
that it terminates with an error.
But let's clean this data up a little bit.
This table isn't necessarily
in the best possible state.
For that I'm gonna switch
back to sqlite-utils again.
So sqlite-utils has a number of
tools designed for cleaning data.
The first is a command called
sqlite-utils transform,
which you can think of as basically
a superpowered alter statement.
So here what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna rename some columns.
I've renamed lat to
latitude long to longitude.
I'll change the type
of that tlength column,
which is the measured
length of the manatee.
I'll change that to a float
from the text that is now.
I'll drop a few columns that I know
aren't particularly interesting.
And I'll reassign the primary key of
that column to be the fieldid column.
So I'm gonna paste this into my terminal
and start datasette running again.
And now when I refresh this page you
can see that we've cleaned up the data
quite a lot. We've got a
small number of columns.
We've renamed latitude and
longitude. We've got that new key.
So this is already beginning
to look quite a bit better.
Let's do something about those dates.
That's not my ideal date format.
I like them to be ISO
formatted. And for this,
we're going to use another sqlite-utils
command - sqlite-utils convert.
What this does is it lets you select one
or more columns and then run a Python
function against those
columns. In this case,
I'm going to use a built-in
recipe called r.parsedatetime to
transform those columns. So I run that,
it churns away and it applies that
function to all 13,000 rows in the data.
And now when I start datasette back up
again you can see that those dates have
been converted and are now in that ISO
format that's somewhat easier to work
with. Let's do one last thing here.
I'm gonna facet my dcode and then
I'm gonna facet by mortality.
And you'll notice that these
numbers are suspiciously similar.
It looks like dcode 1 corresponds with
human related watercraft collision.
All of these dcodes are actually just
numeric codes for these mortalities.
So let's clean the data up further by
extracting those out into a separate
table. I'm going to extract these two
columns from that locations table.
I'm going to rename mortality to name in
the resulting table and that resulting
table's going to be called mortality,
like that. So I paste that in here.
And now if I hit refresh on this table,
it's given me an error because I'm trying
to facet by a decode column that no
longer exists. But here we go.
So now we have a new column called
mortalityid and you'll notice that these
right here are hyperlinks through
to a record in another table.
I can go up to that table
and see here they are,
they've got their decodes and they've
got their names and datasette is smart
enough to spot when a foreign key table
has a column called name and it will use
that as the label on the hyperlink.
That works for faceting too.
So this latitude and
longitude column looks fun.
Let's do something interesting with that.
Datasette support plug-ins and if you
go to the datasette website and look at
the plug-ins
[inaudible], you'll see a list of
81 plug-ins that have been released
for datasette so far. I can search
for map and see there are a
few options for mapping plugins.
This one here, datasette-cluster-map
looks like it might be what we want.
So I'm going to run datasette install
dataset-cluster-map. And this goes ahead
and installs that plugin. And now when
I run datasette again, the plugin has
now kicked in. The plugin looks for the
latitude and longitude columns.
If it finds them it plots their
data on a map. I can actually
load all 13 and a half
thousand points and start seeing a pretty
good indication of where it's dangerous
to be a manatee just through clicking
through and browsing that map on its own.
And this also works with the facets.
So if I click through to the human
related floodgate and canal lock,
I can see a map of just those incidents
that featured that cause of mortality.
So we're doing pretty well.
We started with a CSV file.
We've turned it into a much cleaner
database structure and now we've got a
visualization too. Let's share
this with the rest of the world.
And I'm going to deploy this
using a serverless hosting
program called cloud run
by Google cloud.
And cloud run provides a very inexpensive
way to run stateless web applications
online. The word stateless
is very important.
Normally you'd expect a database
application to be full of state,
but it turns out if your database is
read-only, if it's a sqlite database file,
you can literally package it up as part
of that docker container and deploy it
directly to a serverless hosting provider.
So I'm going to run
datasette publish cloudrun,
and I'm gonna call the service manatees.
I'm passing a little bit of metadata and
I'm gonna tell it to install a couple
of plugins as well, that
cluster mapp plugin,
but also the datasette GraphQL one.
So I paste that in here and it's going
to package everything up into a docker
container, push that docker
container up to Google cloud,
then build the container and they'll
then deploy it and assign a URL.
And that normally takes
about 60 to 70 seconds.
At the end of that it gives me a URL.
I can pop that open and here is how
our brand new manatees database with
that extra metadata. Click
through to locations.
And I can see those locations on that map.
And remember we installed
that GraphQL plugin.
I can actually click on this cog here
and access a GraphQL API for those
locations. This even goes as far as
expanding those foreign key relationships,
in this case the mortality one,
and nesting those together as
part of that GraphQL query.
So we now have a full blown GraphQL
API for the manatee carcass locations,
in addition to the JSON API and the
visual interface for exploring that data.
So hopefully that gives you a good
idea of the kind of tooling I've been
building here.
I mentioned plugins earlier - as you saw
datasette has over 80 plugins driving
all kinds of additional
functionality through authentication,
different ways of visualizing things,
geospatial plugins that can do more
complex things with geospatial data.
But the other side of
the datasette project,
these tools for creating
these sqlite database files,
I showed you sqlite-utils already.
I also have a whole family of tools for
converting other formats and APIs into
sqlite. I've got GitHub to sqlite,
which pulls down your data from github
about issues and issue comments and
commits. Twitter sqlite does the
same thing with your Twitter data.
And the goal here is I'm trying to
increase that range of things that can be
represented as sqlite, partly so
that you can use them with datasette.
But also because I think sqlite is a
fantastic sort of interoperable standard
for archiving and sharing
data just on its own.
The last trick I'll show
you with datasette is that
you can also use it to build
websites. In fact, datasette.io,
the official website,
is itself running on datasette. Datasette
allows you to set up custom templates.
So I have a custom
template for the homepage.
It's got a database table here full of
news, which is shown on the homepage.
The entire thing is built out
of this GitHub repository.
Something I've been exploring a lot
recently isvthis idea of using GitHub
actions to automate data
processing and publishing.
So every time I push a commit to the
datasette.io repository a script runs that
builds all of these sqlite databases
and then deploys them using datasette
publish directly from this,
GitHub actions workflow.
I've been calling this the baked
data architectural pattern.
The key idea here is that for websites
that don't change particularly often,
content-oriented websites,
you can bake a read-only copy of
your data alongside the code of your
application and you can deploy them as
a single unit. As I mentioned earlier,
serverless hosting providers like cloud
run make this incredibly inexpensive,
extremely robust and these scale
amazingly well because as you accept more
traffic you just spin up more instances.
So I hope I've piqued your interest.
If you want to learn more, please
hit the datasette.io website.
If you want to talk to me
about this stuff in person,
I run an office hour sessions on a Friday
where you're welcome to book a slot
and we can have a conversation about
what you can do with datasette,
but also things you might want
to do that aren't possible yet.
Because I'm always looking for ways to
expand out and improve the software.